hello and welcome it's June 7th 2023
we're in active live stream 54.1
discussing mathematical foundations for
a compositional account of the Bayesian
brain so
welcome to the active Institute we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
this is a recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
to learn more about live streams and
other projects head over to
activeinference.org
and
we're here today in active stream 54.1
we are
in our first discussion with the author
of the work mathematical foundations for
a compositional account of the Bayesian
brain
today in 54.1 we're going to say hello
then
be on with it and see where it all goes
together so we'll begin with
introductions
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California
six months ago was quite unfamiliar with
category Theory and have had quite a fun
Journey with Ali and Dean and I guess
Toby via stigmergic proxy so really
looking forward to this discussion and
I'll pass to Dean and then Ollie
thanks Dan I'm Dean I'm here at Calgary
um
my goal in in joining this group was to
take the idea as we got in the one of
the previous slides the idea of
practicing applied active inference I
see the potential through category
theory of making that
even more accessible more possible and
so I'm really excited to have the author
with us today and maybe have a look at
what that means and I'll pass it over to
Ali
hello I'm Ali I'm an independent
researcher Premier run
um
and as I said in that zero I'm quite
excited uh to be here to discuss this
magnificent dissertation with its author
uh and uh well I mean in the past
several months we did our best to uh
understand and dissect it as best as we
could but obviously we have many many uh
questions uh that I'm looking forward to
uh discuss them with
so Toby
thanks again for joining please lead us
off with just any introduction and
background that's going to set the stage
maybe how the the work came to be and
that would be great so thanks again yes
great no well thanks Dan and and all of
you guys for hosting me and and I need
the courage to read my thesis which uh
as you noticed it's a kind of strange
mix of things it's kind of both the
research work and as I noticed
um what are you saying in the in the
previous stream that it's at this kind
of Frontier of knowledge and of course
it needs to be but I also because this
language is so kind of unfamiliar to
people and because I think it you know
will prove to be very useful Across The
Sciences
um I really wanted to make it kind of
legible to people so you know for people
to read the the thesis but also like my
research
and kind of understand what I was saying
effectively how it came about was
yeah I was supposed to be studying
um interactions between frontal cortex
and hippocampus circuits in the brain
and at the sort of time of trying to get
started with that
um obviously I was kind of interested in
the free energy principle and active
inference and all of that
um but I found that there was a lot of
kind of you know as I've said in in the
thesis and as you talked about in the
previous
um stream and probably in previous in
discussions before that as well there's
a lot of kind of you know each dip each
research group has its own language and
uh these different groups you know they
don't
necessarily talk to each other in a way
that is kind of an efficient kind of
communication each you know group of
people is interested in their own thing
and one of the things I like about
um the free energy principle and about
active inference is that it's this nice
sort of General framework for adaptive
systems and so it is in itself a good
place to kind of situate an
understanding of systems like the brain
um and other adaptive systems
but of course it it doesn't you know
immediately resolve this problem of well
the problem that was for me a kind of
confusion about like what's going on in
these circuits and how should I
understand what one person says in
relationship to what another person says
about you know this bit of the brain or
this interaction
and so
in the process of kind of trying to
understand what was going on there and
to resolve in part the confusion I had
about predictive coding itself and you
know the complexities of all these
models I was encountering I kind of
resolved to replace that confusion with
another kind of confusion which is the
you know what is all this crazy category
Theory stuff
and you know so you might think okay
well that's mad what's the point of that
you've just made everybody's life a lot
harder it's kind of like that XKCD comic
where you've got all of these different
standards and you know we decided to
like come together and and make a new
standard and in fact this is happening I
think and like I don't know what it was
in
in cellular biology maybe I heard John
Baez talking about this yesterday that
you know they
have lots of different standards for
writing down diagrams for describing
like interacting like biological
processes and the other kind of
scientific community in in that area has
set up a kind of mediating body to kind
of try to you know form like bring
together all of these diagram languages
um but they weren't really able to do so
so they still they instead of just
coming up with one new standard they
came up with three new standards to try
to unify these things and the travel you
know I had or have with these different
languages or different sort of syntaxes
for talking about scientific things is
that
not only are they all different but
they're kind of all ad hoc and so the
reason why I feel that there's promise
in replacing this confusion of this of
of so many different ideas I mean of
girls it's great to have this kind of
ecosystem of ideas about how these
complicated systems work
but it's still very ad hoc and confusing
and so instead of just coming up with a
new ad hoc and confusing way of
understanding
these things I was kind of hoping to use
a language which is maybe kind of
universal in some sense like it's really
about or it's really capturing like how
we think and maybe also like how the
world is actually you know built up
um but in particular it seems to capture
something of how we think and so you
know the fundamental theorem of category
Theory says that you shall know a
concept by the company it keeps to adapt
the kind of that that sort of motto of I
think um
birth from Linguistics that you should
know a word by the company it keeps
um that that's really like at the heart
of how we come to understand things in
the world and I think the math that is
category Theory captures that very
nicely and very precisely and at the
same time enforces a kind of discipline
and so I know it is quite like hard
going reading this kind of research work
this kind of introduction to all this
new stuff
but you know in part that's because you
know when you're being disciplined is
hard and doing things very formally
precisely does require a bit of
well you know a lot of uh dedication
um but that isn't to say that it's not
worth it or that these ideas even used a
bit informally somewhere down the line
might not be useful at least to sort of
frame the way we think about things
um so I hope to be you know some use in
helping not only sort of change the
confusions that we have but also like
modulate them in a kind of way that will
be sort of useful for people
awesome great starting place
Ali ordin
where can we um begin how can we replace
some of our
prior confusions with a new and
different confusion
all you want to go first yeah can I ask
a quick question of Toby Toby when you
were talking about when you actually saw
all of these standards so you know you
were the sort of
what you were the
you were the Hub of all of these
standards you saw sort of all around you
can you maybe speak to
the idea of what you perceived or what
you sensed was the stabilizing function
of those standards but also the
searching function because of course you
had gone out and realized there were all
of these different
standards at play I remember it in a in
a previous professional life of mine
having to have um
Chief Financial officers and their math
sit sit at the table with engineers and
their math and them talking right past
one another and making no sense to each
other and I had to be kind of the medium
between them so that their math would
actually
get a little bit sticky and they'd be
actually be able to understand and
interpret one another in your in your
experience with this how did that play
out the both the stabilization through
the standards and the search
well I I I guess I should begin by
saying that I'm
um existed still this is still like
ongoing and nor am I an expert in all of
these different standards um but the
thing that I kind of at least noticed
right that was that
people use languages like you know
Bayesian inference or reinforcement
learning or dynamical systems to talk
about certain bits of the brain that I
was interested in
um
and they kind of just plug all these
ideas together and it sometimes and it's
fine so you want to write a paper and
it's about a particular phenomenon and
it's great you maybe come up with some
nice model and you you know you put
people in MRI scanners and that the the
quantities and the you know in the sort
of bold signal correspond to quantities
in your model and that's that's great it
says that maybe this bit of the brain is
doing that
um I mean we can argue about MRI at some
other time but it doesn't really tell
you about how that little model you've
got interacts with the rest of the brain
or the rest of the world and so if you
care about like this whole complicated
thing you want to know how do these
parts actually talk to each other
um and so I was just fortunate
at this kind of beginning of this
um in some sense to be in the right
place at the right time so I kind of
knew there were these different you know
ingredients all being put into these
different models and you know
only yeah I'm only sort of familiar with
some of them but I could still see that
they had sort of similar structure and
that was in part because I had been
going to you know some applied category
Theory meetings or talks and seen that
say
um
economic games which are very closely
related to reinforcement learning have
this kind of bi-directional structure
where an agent tries to sort of
effectively in some sense choose they
make an observation and they sort of do
this kind of
forward projecting kind of thing and
choosing an action at the same time as
saying okay well if supposing I take
this action like what would the payoff
be and that's this kind of backwards
facing thing and then you can sort of
chain that process and think well if I
do this in multiple stages like how does
the utility I get at the end of this
yeah multi-stage process like feedback
to the utility I'm going to get having
taken just one step right now
and that's kind of that's a similar sort
of bi-directional thing to what happens
in active info or like in well in
predictive coding specifically where uh
like a little circuit is saying okay
well I need given that my like high
level beliefs about what's causing this
like sensory data I need to sort of
retro fits the actual sensory data to
kind of come up with a new belief about
what those causes are
and so that seemed to me to have the
same kind of structure
um a similar thing also happens in um
back prop in machine learning where you
have say some neural network in it and
it kind of you know you feed forward
some information through the network and
it say does a classification and then
you have some some training system which
says okay well actually you have this
error and then you need to sort of back
propagate that to update you know say
some parts of the model on the basis of
that so that also has this kind of
bi-directional structure
um and it just was fortunate that at
this time people were talking talking a
lot about these kind of bi-directional
processes and you know so I was thinking
about these things at the same time I
was kind of thinking about you know the
application of Bayesian inference and I
kind of noticed that you know they had
the same structure and I kind of wanted
to figure out what was going on there
like really sort of pinned down
what what it was that made like this
kind of predictive coding circuit have
this kind of shape in some sense
because as I think you've also talked
about
um and as I've kind of mentioned a few
minutes ago that you know individual
predictive coding circuit isn't an
isolated system right it's part of like
this hierarchical thing and so you have
one little circuit connected to another
circuit and that whole
conglomeration of circuitry is supposed
to do something quite Grand but at the
same time it's made of smaller parts
um and I think the the main one of the
major confusions I had at the beginning
was okay so you have this like
big
um generative model with lots and lots
of factors and you go through it and you
try to derive like the differential
equations
that give you the sort of predictive
coding Dynamics by saying okay well yeah
we're going to minimize the free energy
and you have this complicated thing with
lots of sums in it and it seems like
very intimidating to try to like come up
with that differential equation even
though actually when you sort of look at
this the kind of the look at the process
that you're doing is quite kind of
mechanical because effectively you're
doing the same transformation to each
factor of this model
and so that also hinted that there was
this kind of compositionality thing
going on in these systems okay you not
only do you see that these kind of this
bit of the brain is has this kind of
modularity but you also get a sense of
that modularity in that derivation
you're doing
um and so what I wanted to do was to
capture both of these things one is the
kind of shape of the circuitry and the
other is like how
to somehow save the efforts of having to
kind of red arrive everything reach
different case
and that kind of
formalization of this process
corresponds to a kind of functor reality
you get when effectively the functor
reality means you preserve compositional
structure and so what you want to do is
you want to say okay well what's the
compositional structure of the thing
that the function starts with like the
process starts with and that's the
compositional structure of Bayesian
inference itself
and then you want to say okay well
what's the compositional structure of
the kind of dynamical systems which is
the thing you're trying to get to and
how do you map from one to the other in
a way that preserves that structure and
so that's kind of what I was doing in
this thesis is just saying okay what are
the structures I need and how do I
relate them
um and you know it turned out that there
were a lot of details that I had to
write them all down
um but the kind of basic idea I hope is
quite simple it's just trying to say
what are those kind of sim like the kind
of individual components like the kind
of Lego plots and how do they like
connect together
and how can I sort of you know relate
this the kind of Lego blocks of one
thing with the Lego box of another in a
way that's kind of preserves the shapes
um
and so yeah it's it's kind of is kind of
Mammoth thing but the kind of
fundamental idea is quite simple and I
think it's kind of like how when
if you're if you're like programming a
computer you can write in a high level
language or you can write something like
low-level language and if you wanted to
you could write in
Assembly Language
and category theory is like
a language where you start with the kind
of Assembly Language and you build up a
high level language
within the language itself in some sense
and so if you really want to start with
at the very beginning like I did with
the definition of category and then
build up to this big thing you have to
make a lot of steps because like
Assembly Language is really simple and
it's you know it's just like single
instructions that your processor does
and so getting all the way to something
like Zoom that can do a video call is
quite complicated and so people don't
they start with a high level language
but the thing that people strive for in
designing high-level languages is to set
them up in such a way that they're sort
of the the abstractions are quite nice
or sort of modular
and so that's what I'm trying to do with
using category theory is to kind of find
abstractions that are modular in a
similar kind of way and I know
um
on the previous call
um Dan you mentioned
um the the kind of analogy between like
typing in this category theoretic sense
and in the programming sense and they're
quite similar
um the category Theory sense is kind of
a much
sort of more General bigger idea it has
a lot it sort of incomes there's all
kinds of things
um
but you could imagine somewhere down the
line having a programming language and
that you know people are trying to build
these things but having a programming
language where you could express
anything you could in you know category
Theory and you know I to be honest find
it quite intense
and quite sometimes mechanical and
tedious how to prove that certain
categorical structures satisfies the
coherence conditions that it has to
satisfy like you know lacks
associativity or monoidality or
something like this there are a lot of
like diagrams you have to check commute
or something and much of the time that
checking is quite tedious and someday I
hope that we all have tools that we
could say okay well I'm going to spell
out what my structure is and the tool
will just check that it satisfies all
the axioms and so you know I know you
guys had to Wade through a lot of that
stuff in the thesis but it's kind of
meant manually necessary right now but
in the future it might not be and then
we can use this high-level language in a
much more kind of liberal way I hope
that would be great sorry I've been
roughly overrated so I'll stop there
awesome
great or go to a question in the chat
Mark wrote
applied category Theory and active
inference have tremendous promise I
confess I have not yet read this
dissertation it would be helpful to
describe a specific engineering
application for the work
so what do you see as approximate and
and or distal engineering applications
here
so one of the things
that I hope
could be produced soon as an engineering
application
is a general
modeling framework for building kind of
complicated active inference systems
that might include lots of Parts lots of
you know agents
um kind of like
um
something that
my colleague Jules Hedges wants in
cybernetics more generally something
like kind of programming language maybe
that incorporates
um
all of these kind of strange cybernetic
structures I mentioned earlier like
reinforcement learning and like back
propping machine learning and Bayesian
inference they all have this kind of
bi-directionality and so you should be
able to have this kind of modeling
environment which allows you to
incorporate all of these things in a
kind of nice way
um
but I think before we get something
quite as Grand as a whole new sort of
modeling environment I think just having
tools to help us build
um you know approximate an active
inference systems that are really nicely
compositional is is one thing that I you
know hope to come out of this
uh to be honest I don't know very well
what the general tooling is like for
this kind of thing right now I know that
there's SPM I know that there's like Pi
mdp for certain kinds of problem
um but I don't know how sort of General
they are
um another thing that you would get if
you have this kind of toolkit because of
the kind of modularity of category
theory is you you should be able to plug
it into other things that exist already
so
um one of the things that's particularly
of interest to me at the moment is kind
of multi-agent systems
um and sort of building trying to
understand how we could build
um
something like or simulate things like
you know something like a corporation or
some kind of yeah some kind of society
structure where you've got lots of
active inference agents coming together
to pursue a sort of common shared goal
um how can you kind of
effectively distribute that goal sharing
across systems they could be like little
robotic systems say or something like
that or you know agent or like I I don't
know because precisely I'm kind of like
an abstract thinker but I yeah I think
like being able to kind of
control or like
modulate the performance of these kind
of
distributed multi-agent like active
infant systems might be quite a cool
thing yeah to be able to build
so that that's kind of like
a kind of maybe
sort of
flavor the kind of thing this tooling
gives you
um I suppose for me this particular work
was really about
trying to encourage people to use this
language to understand things more
clearly
um
so
yeah there's a lot of stuff that I hope
we can understand well at least I can
understand more clearly
um
sure
awesome thank you Ali
thank you uh yes so in this paper by uh
Christoph walterwitch
um are there category theoretical
explanations of physical phenomena
he argues that category Theory by itself
does not and cannot provide any
mathematical explanations for a physical
phenomena so the idea here is that a
category theory is merely a meta Theory
to kind of
uh to what kind of bookkeeping or house
holding of the physical theories and
it's not a tool to construct the
mathematical theory of physical
phenomena itself uh I'm not sure I agree
with this argument entirely because
um in one sense some of the most
profound aha moments in the history of
science obviously results from looking
at
a pre-existing Theory or a model from a
novel angle and I believe category
Theory can provide such novel
perspectives even when looking at some
established and pre-existing models or
theories so
what do you uh I'm curious to know uh
your opinion about this so do you think
uh category Theory can actually provide
uh mathematical explanations for uh I
mean either in cognitive science
Neuroscience or even other areas other
scientific disciplines as well
I think it's a it's a subtle question
um right now it's probably largely the
case that the role of category theory is
kind of this I'm not I think it's like
like bookkeeping but like clarification
too
um
bookkeeping if you think of it as a very
general way of like trying to account
for the
the things you're thinking about very
precisely and not sort of Miss details
like if you your books don't balance you
can't miss some payment or some debt
um I think that's quite a nice analogy
but I think one of the goals of quite a
lot of people or not maybe I mean the
fair chunk of the community
um particularly that which comes from a
sort of more abstract mathematical side
of
um category Theory
um one of their goals is to try to
recast
a lot of how we think in kind of purely
categorical language so one of the
things that category Theory allows us to
do is to kind of
formalize
in some sense patterns that crop up all
over the place using the notion of
universal Construction
and
the thing about Universal constructions
is that you have like
some little pattern and if you know that
you can
instantiate that pattern in your
category
that you have like some object which
kind of
captures the essence of that pattern and
you don't need to say
be able to kind of write down all of the
specifics of that object you know sort
of a priori because the kind of
universality gives you a recipe for
constructing it it gives you it in in
some sort of unique way and so you know
that if you have this universality you
can always you can always like access
this object and yeah so I'm talking very
generally but because of that
um one thing that people try to do is to
try to say okay well what it you know
we've got these things that we're
interested in
um in say physics like you know the
principle of least action or like the
nature of
um
space time or something like that
can we express those things as kind of
universal constructions
um
all
for instance in a completely different
realm like we may have some process
which is something that we're interested
in on the computer like
um the migration of data and databases
can we write that down in a way that
doesn't have any kind of ad hoc
ingredients it only is built from
Universal constructions these are things
that we can just write down kind of
abstract sort of axioms in the language
of category Theory and that kind of
gives us
the the process or the structure that we
that we want
um this kind of line of work is
often called like synthetic
something like synthetic
um you know
probability Theory or synthetic
um physics or synthetic topology or
something like that and it means you
sort of start from these kinds of very
high level categorical ideas
and then you sort of end up with a
characterization of the essence of the
thing you're interested in in physics I
kind of
um a simple example of this
um which I Supply in a kind of
relatively feeble efforts to say that
it's not true that pedigree Theory
doesn't give you a characterization of
things in
um physics
so there is a category of say
topological spaces and the morphisms
between them are continuous functions
and there's amorphism a category rather
of sets and the morphism between the
sets are functions
and of course underlying every
continuous function is a plane function
and so there is a functor from the
category of topological spaces to the
category of sets which just forgets
the the topological structure of the
spaces because every topological space
has an underlying set of points
so you have this forgetful bunker
and this forgetful functor has two
adjoints and one of the things the
category Theory teaches you is that
adjunctions give you this universality
so adjoint functors are characterized
uniquely by their kind of the
satisfaction of this adjunction property
so these two adjoints to this forgetful
functor one gives you what are called
um discrete spaces so if you take a set
you can turn it into a topological Space
by thinking of all the points as little
Islands in this space so there's no like
connectivity between them
and that's called a kind of discrete
space on that set
and the other adjoint functor
gives you what's called the Indiscreet
or sometimes co-discrete space where all
of the points are sort of collected into
one big like Island so you they're also
connected together so it's like a sort
of fully connected graph
and of course that's very different from
the discrete space and it's different
from like the space time or the space
that you live in
um which has a particular kind of you
know connectivity like you can't walk
through walls
um and so you know people try to use
these things particularly use
adjunctions to characterize things like
Properties or spaces another thing that
comes out to a jointness
um and this is something that like
um can let you read about uh later
because it'll take me the rest to talk
to try to explain
um but the you might be familiar from
logic that you have these quantifiers
you have existential and Universal
quantifiers
um and you can do things with these
quantifiers like you can say
um you could sort of compose them
together so you get things like for all
X there exists a y such that this
and you can think sometimes of these
Composites or these compositions of
quantifiers as like maybe like modal
operators like you can sort of decompose
necessity and possibility in terms of
the compositions of of logical
quantifiers
but the kind of weird thing about
bondifiers is that they too arise out of
an adjunction
um it's kind of like they are left and
right adjoints to substitution so if you
have a proposition you can like
substitute the term intimate
and the the adjunction the adjoint
punctures to substitution give you the
quantifiers and you can sort of take
this another step and then you can think
about like composing these adjoint
functors and those give you the modal
operators
and so that's something that comes just
out of category Theory but it's really
sort of fundamental in in sort of logic
and you know we might think there's a
kind of close relationship between
physics and computation or physics and
logic
um or you know physics and information
and information and computation and if
and logic so I think it's not quite true
that there's nothing to be gained from
um thinking about
kind of traditional mathematical things
uh or traditional physical things using
category theory in some sense they you
know doing that really clarifies the
essence of them
um because it tells you what their kind
of universal properties are and you can
then like instantiate those things in
different contexts so one of the things
that you could do is start to think
about
these kind of logical structures in
different contexts and that's kind of
like what type theory is all about and
you could use it to think about the
logic of like dynamical systems or you
could use it to try to characterize
um say like the Universal Property even
of the free energy principle and that's
something that I like to think about
sometimes like how can we think about
active inference systems as like trying
to achieve their goals
is that is that related to these
Junctions that you know come up in sort
of foundations of logic when you look at
them categorically and if it is then
that's quite profound because it tells
you that you know maybe the fep does
have this kind of universality that
people want to claim it does
um so I think you know it it is true
that right now because it's quite early
days
um
category theory is kind of mostly used
for bookkeeping but I guess that might
be because
um there's quite a lot of bookkeeping to
do before we can make the most of this
kind of move
um make the most of using these kind of
universal structures and maybe one day
further in the future where people are
more familiar with this kind of language
and we have this you know big library of
categorical tools and yeah our computer
program our computer sort of modeling
environments and programming languages
know how to like import stuff from this
category just really easily
and so you don't have to do all this
kind of tedious manual stuff maybe like
in the future in that future it'll be
much more common just to say okay well
we're going to start to model things
using these Universal properties you
know off the bat rather than trying to
sort of retrofit them
awesome thank you Toby Ollie
uh yes thank you so much for your
detailed answer and uh again I have a
follow-up question to that so there's
this view in philosophy of science that
views scientific theories
um as not as a kind of Monolithic uh I
mean phenomena or model but rather any
given scientific theory can be viewed as
a population of models so some of those
models are more fundamental than the
others and um
or in terms of manual the Land There are
virtual and actual part of each of Any
Given scientific model so the idea here
is that uh the actual part of scientific
models uh try to capture the context
dependent uh behavior of phenomena or
any physical system but on the other
hand the virtual or more fundamental
part of scientific models or theories
try to somehow capture it's more
abstract and
abstract model of the phenomena in terms
of its topological invariance so do you
think the category Theory can provide a
rigorous language to somehow unify this
view of science uh I mean and to see how
exactly those context dependent part of
scientific theories fit or at least can
be compatible with the
context independent part of scientific
theory is or the virtual part uh because
you see uh in the context dependent uh
or actual models uh scientists usually
try to refine their models to fit the
data as close as possible or at least
approximately uh close enough to be
useful but for the more fundamental
Parts uh comprising of principles axioms
and so on they only try to capture the
topological
um terrain or or the uh I mean the
topological invariance of the models and
how models can be compared in terms of
their uh singularities and topological
shapes
yeah that does sound very familiar I
don't know this kind of work or idea
um in any you know I I haven't come
across this before but it does sound
something that's quite amenable and in
fact you know there seems to be at least
in my mind some alignment between this
kind of sense of virtual that you're
talking about and this kind of
universality that I was talking about
um so you could think of you know a
category of models of particular kinds
as being like inhabited by all of those
things which satisfy these invariants
and then you have different you know
individual instances of these things
um which would be like the objects of
the category and then the the
differences between them other you know
the morphisms and the thing about
morphism in the category is that often
they are the things which preserve the
structure uh in other bits of
mathematics they're called homomorphisms
and that's where the word morphism comes
from
and so you could think of those as they
you know
ways of comparing the models or
translating the models from one to the
other
um but preserving those invariants yeah
and so that that seems to me to capture
some of the idea that you were sketching
um I guess
one thing which may or may not be useful
depending on how you look at it
um the category Theory gives you is it's
obviously kind of a lot more General and
so it allows you to talk about
invariance of kinds that you know more
than just
um
game excuse me um more than just
topological
um in subsets like functor reality is a
kind of
um in like it kind of captures the kind
of invariance as well and saying okay
well we preserve this structure
um
each I mean one just one way of like
looking at a topological spaces to take
its
um
it's what's called it's nerve and so
that that takes a topological space
and turns it into
a category
and you could sort of think of the the
morphisms in that category as like the
the sort of like the paths in that space
or ways to sort of get from one sort of
part of the space to another
um and then you know morphisms
functors between topological spaces
considered in categories like that
they really are just things that
preserve those topological structures
um and so easily like this this language
kind of seems to Encompass the kinds of
things you're saying um
yeah yeah it would be nice yeah I would
I would love somebody to you know make
that connection
oh oh just follow up on this and then
Dean it's a it's a um related comment
from Roman in the chat Roman wrote uh
quoted you in this fractal
quote streaming thinking about the fep
through category theory in relation to
goals maybe allows to prove that fep has
the universality that people claim it
has
and Roman asks didn't Maxwell ramstead
and Dalton's octave devel already kind
of proved this in the Bayesian mechanics
physics of and by belief work
so you're talking about the role of
generalization
what do we gain with the category
theorification of fep
beyond for example the generalizations
that we've seen in Bayesian mechanics
and G Theory over the last year
yeah that's a
it's a question
um I think
Maxwell and Dalton are doing a great job
um
formalizing the ideas of Bayesian
mechanics but that as far as
I'm aware the job isn't done yet
um and so
I
haven't yet seen
yeah I mean I have a particular
aesthetic right and I would like
I would like to see a really clear
recipe of a way to take of like on the
one hand some like or like some machine
that takes in that has like a particular
shape but it's like input shape and it
takes in like a dynamical system of a
particular kind and it gives me back
um like uh the the specification of an
inference problem so that that amical
system is solving
um I think that's what Daisy mechanics
is saying it's saying okay well if we
have a dynamical system that is somehow
kind of you could sort of
look at it and say it has a boundary
it's a Markov blanket
um that you can write down its Dynamics
as if it were
doing free energy minimization that is
solving some inference problem
um
but there's a lot of and I so I think
that statement is true for certain
classes of dynamical systems but it's
not I don't think
the story has been made
like like the questions for me are like
what are the classes
um and what are their what's the essence
of those dynamical systems so
if the result might just depend on like
specific technical criteria which maybe
you think okay well like that that's
kind of like a distraction from this
kind of
abstract principle which we're trying to
get at and so it'll be nice to sort of
know what the actual like Essence is of
the problem that allows us to do this
translation
and then you know there seems to be to
be like questions of
I mean other fairly technical questions
but questions about things like well
what is this boundary thing like how
long does it persist and what does it
mean to separate the thing off and
consider it as having a boundary
um most of the treatments I've seen of
this idea have not been done I've not
been explained or expressed in uh in
this compositional way and so they just
assume you're given a system and a
boundary and then that's kind of it
um
but
you know boundaries come in all kinds of
shapes
um like the boundaries of the cells in
my body are kind of all like glued
together in a particular way and they
form me and I also have a boundary
um and so how
do the kind of local inference problems
that are being solved by those
individual cells
given their gluing amount to the kind of
inference problem that my whole body is
solving
um and I don't think an answer to that
has you know is anywhere near given
right now
um and yet
obviously we're you know we look at
systems out in the world and they all
seem to display this property of
re-energy minimization or at least
something that looks a lot like it
and so it would be nice to be able to
relate those
um those kind of inference problems to
one another
um
so I think there's still a lot to be
done
um just just because we've kind of made
some First Steps doesn't mean that we're
all of the way there
um
but obviously
given my Aesthetics what I would love to
see is this kind of abstract
characterization of this universality
um and I think I yeah I think there's a
way of stating well at least the
structure of that Universal Property
um using this compositional act of
inference language of which the thesis
is apart but effectively it seems to be
something like this adjoint thing that I
was talking about earlier so you on the
one hand you have a like a something
like a functor that takes
um statistical problems and gives you
dynamical systems
that kind of solve those inference
problems
and so that's a function from like you
know statistical yeah what I call
statistical gains into that and
consistent of some kind but of course
you have lots of dynamical systems and
say you know what this
um Bayesian mechanics idea seems to be
saying is that you can go the other way
as well
and maybe this mapping in the other
direction is also factorial and that
would be a way of characterizing this
kind of gluing together of dynamical
systems like I was talking about cells
and ending up with maybe dynamical
statistical games that also have this
kind of gluing property
um but there's still
a fair amount of work to be done
even to get like the basic framework to
spell out that story precisely
um it was work that I'm trying to slowly
get on with at the moment
um
but I think you know some you know the
ingredients to to doing this
in the kind of generality that I would
like that's starting to become clear
um and so hopefully we get there but I
don't think it's I don't think it's sold
yet
awesome yes just so cool to see all
these paths
weaving together
Dean
I I think it's awesome Toby that you in
this conversation have kind of
anti-captored adjointness and comma
jointness because I think that's a huge
part of your work here and
and reading it so here's my here's my
question I
I think and I would like you to maybe
comment on this as though you were
explaining it to a very curious 15 year
old
so on the sort of most basic level when
I hear under sort of a common
adjointness principle the word
bookkeeping I immediately Wonder okay so
what is the partner what's the what's
the thing that's being glued to
to use your metaphor and so
I would glue it to taking receipts
essentially where you have a
stabilization of a record under
bookkeeping
so I get that part and then the taking
receipts is the
stabilization of the change function
right the The Exchange
something that we receive those two
things seem to kind of work together
which then allows for compositionality
and all that other stuff but maybe I
wonder if maybe you could kind of speak
to this idea that something is presented
to us
and then what the category Theory does
is allows us to now start working with
so where does this fit does this fit
under
this superordinate of being a tool or
does it fit under this column directly
adjacent as a as a rule like that's the
part where
I think the adjointness could be really
really helpful in terms of maybe helping
people
see the applicability and not just the
abstraction what's what's your thoughts
on that
so I mean I I yeah so I think um
David Spivak talks about category Theory
as being light a kind of accounting
system
um
or accounting systems plural for
mathematics and I I think he's kind of
quite right then so the way I the way I
see it is like
um
when you you know when you're keeping
books
um particularly if you're sort of using
like this double entry system you're
trying to keep track of the stuff that
kind of flows into and out of your
account uh your company or whatever it
is
um without sort of missing some bits you
see where everything goes
and so that's how I think of this kind
of mathematical language
you have this stuff
um
and it's kind of like some like abstract
collection of things some like maybe
mathematical ideas
and
well a functor takes that stuff and does
something with it and turns it into some
stuff of another kind
um but
yeah it's like this kind of Double Entry
idea but you know when you take
something out of here you have to put it
in here and so you have to sort of keep
track of all the details at least all of
the details that are relevant
to those two
to that flow I suppose
and so when you have an adjunction you
have a way of going from one place to
another and Back Again
without losing trackers and stuff
um it's like a little bit kind of like
you're allowed to lose track of some
stuff but you you know the stuff you've
lost track of because you don't care
about it like you know it like you know
you might you might allow
or
some
you know have some like butter there but
you know how big your buffer is
something like that
so like a little bit like more precisely
like in a junction is a way to map from
one category to another and and Back
Again
in such a way that like the
the two mappings are kind of like
like ideal approximations of the inverse
of some of each other
and that you can sort of measure the
difference between between them
um they sort of like give you it gives
you like an isomorphism of between the
two sets of morphisms of some kind and
that that kind of gives you this nice
kind of structure preservation property
this kind of bookkeeping property
um
I don't I mean so I know that there
there are people out there
um
who have used
category Theory to
um model stock flow diagrams
and so these are used in economics to
measure you know stop flows of stocks
and things like that but they also use
an epidemiology to model
you know the transmission of disease
because that's also like
um a flow of some stock you have people
moving around
um
and so I you know it would be nice to
sort of bring this idea full circle and
have this mathematical language of
bookkeeping actually applied to
bookkeeping
um but I don't I I haven't I don't know
how that would go just yet
but but like you know if we think of if
we think of economies and corporations
as as adaptive systems
or if we somehow kind of translate from
blows of money to like flows of
information but there does seem to be
like an analogy
between that kind of flow and the kind
of flows that we think of in active
inference explicitly
um and you know another thing yeah one
of the things I liked about category
theory is it allows us to make these
analogies in a precise way and so maybe
we can
you know relate these two things quite
clearly I mean I you know it's yet to be
done but I would love to see it
awesome
Dean smiles when his keywords are buzzed
during a response
we'll go to another great question in
the chat from Matt n Matt wrote can you
provide some ideas about the next
necessary steps or milestones for
categorical Theory to be effectively
utilized across research and in
subsequent engineering applications and
I'll just kind of append to that what do
you think at the individual team and
organizational scale
what can we do what Milestones exist to
realize some of these engineering
applications and implications that you
brought up
right so I think the main thing
possibly unfortunately for you guys who
spent a lot of time reading the details
I wrote is that kind of have this
community
um
develop to a stage where the tools that
I mentioned that allow us to kind of use
these category theoretic Concepts
fluently without having to know all of
those like boring and complicated
details
to develop those to a stage where people
are actually you know able to use them
without being kind of like
mathematicians or category Theory domain
experts
um so this is I think starting to happen
I guess yeah
as a result of the kind of needs of the
pandemic
people have developed these tools for
epidemiology I mentioned this stock
flows stuff
and I think you know you can probably
there's like some I can't remember what
it's called unfortunately now
um
so in the Julia programming language
there's this great framework for use for
kind of building
system using
category Theory Concepts
um but of course this doesn't satisfy
the property of not having to be a
category Theory domain expert yet on top
of that people have built using
compositional ideas about Dynamics
Frameworks for you know Building
compositional dynamical Systems and like
compositional models for things like
epidemiology and stuff like that
and you know hopefully we'll get there
also with
um you know statistical modeling and
active inference and all that stuff but
what you know once once you've got that
kind of lower level Library people can
start to build like user interfaces on
top of it and that's the thing that's
starting to happen now with the stock
flow stuff
um and I think the people involved in
that project are
I mean they know that there's like one
kind of heat like major like proprietary
tool for doing this kind of modeling
which is used for you know it's used by
lots of different organizations for
instance it was used by governments for
modeling during the pandemic but it's
not like it's not very collaborative
it's it's not compositional so if you
like have this huge model it's very hard
to like deal with like to modulate just
some small part of it
and so these people are as I say it's
very unfortunate I can't remember all
their names um or the name of the
software but they're building this tool
which allows you to
build up these models just using this
interface but it's built out of this
compositional stuff
um and so it has a lot of the nice
properties that come out of it and of
course you if you if you want you can
sort of delve onto the hood and
understand like actually how it works
and connect it to all this other stuff
and maybe down the line when we've got
really Advanced tools that that will
kind of be able to be done for free and
some nice user interface but I think you
know so if if people want to make the
most of this you know they can sort of
get it involved with that kind of effort
or at least they could sort of get
familiar with
the kind of basic ideas of you know
categorical modeling or compositional
thinking as I like to say these days
um
but I don't I also don't want to like
prescribe to people they have to know
what like a monad is and all that stuff
because you know there are it is
technical it has to be technical because
it's about technical stuff but I mean
it's also trying to be ergonomic and
yeah if if that's your thing you can try
to help make it more so
awesome
Dean
no I I I I I'm waiting because there's a
there's a part of the paper that
that belief updating and the fuzzy of
distributions and stuff I'm gonna want
to talk about that later but I'm I'm
done for now
all right I'll go to a question
submitted by Jr also who created the
syllabus so thanks again Jr for that
amazing work so Jr wrote
um in compositional active inference
from May 17 2021 Toby said I'm with
Valeria on this I think we need to seek
AI alignment for the artificial
intelligences that we already have
things like corporations and social
systems and we should be concentrating
on those right now
could you speak more about how you
envision this kind of application this
is especially interesting in light of
what we spoke about
in the 54.0 regarding Sensor Fusion and
consensus what might this mean for
corporations and social systems
Toby do you mean that uh this between
humans and things kind of like
artificial intelligences or machines and
artificial intelligences in the context
of companies and societies
yeah that's a great question and I think
you know jl's done a great job with the
syllabus which I also had a look at
um yeah yeah I think
it's a good it's a good it's a good like
list of
um material and Concepts to sort of get
get to grips with
um but as the yeah AI alignment it's a
very vexed issue of course
um I know
I mean I've put this to people who are
involved in the
um AI safety community
and some of them say oh well
we concentrate on machine intelligent
rather than corporations because there's
like no hope for making corporations
safe like it's too late they're already
out there so we can't
fix that which is obviously a very sort
of defeatist attitude but maybe it's
right
um to concentrate on a matter where they
think that they can actually have an
influence
um but I do nonetheless still think that
corporations are like super
intelligences we they've been
made out of code but the code isn't
a traditional computer programming
language it's the legal programming
language that makes up their contracts
but those contracts will determine how
they operate and are executed on a thing
which is a bit like a computer like the
legal system
um you know you go into court it
processes the contract and it explains
what the outcome is going to be it's a
you know it's like a computer but it's
like made up of people
um and you know they have you know goals
and yeah desires and they take actions
and they receive information from the
world and so yeah they're a lot like
um well yeah AI systems but it's nice
because we can pun on AI and have it
mean both artificial intelligence and
active influence
um
so yeah so that's like a long Preamble
one of the things that
at least as far as I know right now the
active immigrants literature doesn't
talk an awful lot about at least not
very precisely is this notion of sense
of fusion so you can have like
two say you have like two yeah so if you
think about the brain again you've got
like two like neural little neural
circuits next to each other
and they're making predictions about
two visual receptive fields
um but those visual receptive Fields
they kind of often overlap and so
what
we might want a system like the brain to
do is to be able to kind of glue the two
inferences that those circuits made
together over this overlap so that you
get like this you know unitary
perception like we don't just see a
bunch of independent patches of the
world we see like this kind of glued
together thing even though you know the
way it's been in third is through lots
of like individual systems next to one
another
and so it's it's
quite you know on you know it's quite
clear how to put two things next to each
other mathematically you just take their
sort of product
um that you do then you just do them
side by side but when you need to when
you want them to sort of glue together
in this way
um you might encounter some problems
like you might have one make one
inference and one make another inference
and so you get like a disagreement
and then you need to start to say okay
well what's what's going on there like
what is the nature of this disagreement
is it saying that can be resolved by
like say you know passing some messages
between the two systems or do we need to
just like ignore some of the data or is
there fundamentally some like Paradox
which means that we can't resolve this
disagreement
excuse me um and so in mathematics
there's a lot of theory that's been done
about precisely this question
in topology in a kind of abstract way
um related to the field of what's called
cohomology which is all about like
measuring like obstructions to doing
this kind of gluing thing
and sort of in this world of like
applied topology people talk about
um
algorithms for resolving disagreements
and and things like that and they often
have the flavor of like diffusion you
can sort of think of diffusion as like
smoothing out disagreements like because
you're just sort of like letting stuff
propagate
um
something there maybe could be said
about like how these diffusion models
work in generative AI but I haven't
really thought about that
um and so you know maybe maybe there's
something to be done for you know
political systems or corporations like
maybe we can look at how
you know the mathematics says we can
resolve these disagreements and
Implement better processes in our
organizations that are inspired by
those algorithms or kind of universal
properties
and you know maybe that'll make the
world a kind of more harmonious place or
maybe it will just help us build
um
you know systems
in the future which resolve
disagreements better and this is one of
the reasons why I was
um
talking about you know multi-agent
systems before
um I know
this is the thing that sometimes people
think about in the context of you know
blockchain systems and things like that
which are actually actively composed of
lots of different participants
um
but I don't know yet
how we
yeah my
all pan out I mean ultimately you know
the question of alignment is really
about do the goals of this other system
um disagree with my goals and you know
if the other system has more power than
you then ultimately there's probably not
much you can do about it regardless of
whether there's
oh that where there exists some
algorithm that might help you smooth it
out
um so I I think
I I hope at least that by looking at how
like the mathematics says we can
optimally resolve disagreements or
smooth them out or patch things together
or build kind of multi-agent systems
that will help us build things in the
future in such a way that we don't get
to a situation where the systems we're
working with are actually aligned
against us say
um but obviously we can't really
guarantee it we actually have to sort of
do some work but it's nice that at least
um the framework of active inference
allows us to talk about that at least
right so you know we can say like oh I
have these beliefs about the world and
there's other agent that has these
beliefs about the world and
then you know we can express these
beliefs in a mathematical framework
which is amenable to using these tools
from cohomology
and applied topology to be able to start
to make use of that work that's already
being done
um it's to me not so clear how you would
do that if you're not working in this
active inference world and you're
working say with just reinforcement
learning
um
I I know
there are similar questions about how to
kind of glue together preference
functions in economics
um and I think
for me the simplest way to kind of
understand those questions is to kind of
turn those preference functions into
distributions Over States and then use
this kind of
um sort of more active inferency
language so think about it
um so yeah again we don't you know we're
just at the start of this process but
like it sounds like we should be able to
you know make use of this wealth of
tooling which has been developed in
other fields
um because we're putting this into
this kind of modular categorical
language we should be able to kind of
you know put put these two modules
together and make make the most of them
thanks
I'm gonna go to a different sort of
question here
I'm a new uh play dissertation roulette
but I kind of know where I'm going to go
and uh I'm gonna skip to a diagram
it's a diagram at the end of chapter six
and it looks like this
so
what do we see here
what
happens
in this graphical arrangement
it doesn't have to be ultra specific
about defining every variable but
does right what is what matters here
that's apology or the geometry is it an
arbitrary visual layout but you're
conveying something about the
connectivity or is it read from left to
right or is there a certain way to
understand or just approach these
diagrams which in slightly smaller forms
or larger forms we see peppered
throughout category Theory and your
dissertation
so okay yeah so here what I'm trying to
do
is say that
if you have
a
like hierarchical predictive coding
system
if you if you take like the form of two
parts that are sort of plugged into one
another and this is the the G and the h
if you like do predictive coding on
G
and you sort of plug that into h
and then you do predictive coding on H
with that input
it's the same thing as doing
predictive coding directly on the two
parts
as if they were one thing at the start
so what I mean is if you have so like
here we've got
like a hierarchical system
again the parts of the hierarchy are G
and H
and we could do two things we could
either
apply predictive coding to the two parts
and then glue those predictive coding
systems together
or we could glue like
the G and H together
and then apply predictive coding
to GH the glued system
and what this bit of this result is
saying is if you do those two processes
you get the same dynamical system and
that's that's saying that this
predictive coding thing
um at least with this sort of laplacian
scheme is functorial
so in this diagram
um it is red
from left to right I mean of some sense
you know you can Orient these diagrams
however you want as long as you're clear
about how you how the information flows
um and if I remember rightly what would
what we've got is we've got
some like
um
a yes we've got X and Y so I think um
so we've got one system which is
predicting X and one system which is
predicting why and I'm not totally sure
what p and Q are but I guess they relate
to X and Y
EP
um and you've got some stuff that's
coming into
the predictive coding system h of G
and some other stuff which is coming in
and going to H of H
and these give you like updated States
so in predictive coding with this
LaPlace algorithm what happens is that
you you know you get this new
observation that comes in and you look
at the error
on
you know your you know between that
observation and your prediction and you
update your prediction according to the
sort of direction that error points you
in
and so that's what these HG and H
systems are doing
but because it's a hierarchical system
this like second layer
which
yeah the second layer requires you to
take in the prediction of the first
layer
so if you sort of follow in the flow of
information
h h
akes in inputs from gamma
gamma is the kind of
um the predictive channel the predictive
part of G
and so that feeds into h
and the update
of G which is a little layer above age
requires the the
newly updated belief from H right so
that's going sort of up in the causal
hierarchy
and so if you sort of follow the flow in
as well into this G update function at
the top h of G
you see that it gets an input from the
sigma function
and that's the
that's the new belief emitted by the H
system in in this part of the proof at
least that was the notation I used
and so this is a saying if you do
predictive Cody on these two bits it it
has this structure which is you know you
do the forwards pass down through the
system G and then h
and that gives you a prediction at the
kind of lowest level
and then you you take your observation
which is I think the thing you get in
here in Z yeah that's what Z is it goes
into H you get an updated belief that
comes out in the form of the sigma
and then gets passed to the first level
of the hierarchy
which is used to give you the highest
level belief
great well it's awesome because in so
many papers
we see what I guess people expect and
prefer which is you should be able to
make a nested model here and have
communicating agents here and do
sophisticated affective inference in
this way and it's like we're already
playing with the Legos in a sense and
talking about it like it's a total Play
Shop so to understand
in a way that is worthy of dissertation
research
some of that substrate it's basic Lego
research and how do you know when you're
working you describe this as a result
how do we know I mean can I just draw a
line from here to here or can I just uh
make a d and just have D you know
connect to gamma what rules do you keep
a guidebook or recipe on the table what
rules help us know what
edges and shapes you can even draw and
when you describe the manual checking
are you looking for what
right so yeah this is this is a good
question
um so yeah this is like it is like a
language so it has a syntax
um and
that syntax is like I mean it's like the
grammar right and it tells you what
things
make sense to say
um
and so you only say those things
don't we all don't we all no but that
but it's it's that's what I am laughing
because often you want to like play with
the grammar right
and so sometimes you're like oh well you
know I'm it feels like I'm not allowed
to like draw this thing like I'm not
allowed to connect this box to this
other box in this way but like I really
want to do that
and it's actually that's not a bad thing
you shouldn't do it in that diagram
where it doesn't make sense but you
should take that feed again and reflect
on it and say
oh but that's saying that maybe this
language this diagram syntax is missing
something important
and then you should yeah trust your
intuitions there and say okay well like
actually what do I need to do to this
diagram language
to make it like
allow me to do that move that I wanted
to do to draw that thing I wanted to
draw
and so that that you know suggests that
there's like you know you're you're
walking down you're walking through like
a valley and you can see there's a hill
over here and there's something peeking
out over it and you're like actually
there's nothing over there I need to be
able to see and so you have to like move
over towards a different place to be
able to get to that to that place
um and so you should do that right then
that's fine but the reason why I said at
the beginning don't just draw it in your
diagram is because then that means your
diagram doesn't mean anything and that's
that's worse so it this is part of the
reason that it's actually requires
using this kind of mathematical
formalism really using mathematics
generally requires this discipline
um because you don't you don't want to
say things that don't make sense it's
kind of a if you have an intuition you
should do it justice and
and and like treat it seriously and you
know you probably get more out of it by
figuring out what's missing
so like you know with this particular
kind of string diagram language you
can't just get used to reading them
right so I you know that these little
black dots mean copy some information so
you if you see the first one or like or
like the second one on why you know you
go from why you go into this copier and
you just send the information
to both of those outputs
if you read like um Bob cooker's work or
say his book on
um
his book picturing Quantum processes
which is all about uh quantum theory
using this string diagram language
um
there's a lot of like there are lots
lots of different rules for like
stuff you can do with these languages
languages like you have colored like
spiders equals them which are like
colored versions of these black dots
and you know you there are things you're
allowed to do like if you have two
spiders next to each other that are the
same color you can sort of merge them to
be a spider with like as many legs as
the two of them
and if they don't have the same color
then you can sort of split them apart
and like that's that those kinds of
those kinds of moves
are like
you know part of the syntax of this
language but it's a it's a human
language and so people
developed it and they realized that they
could do some things and they realize
that they couldn't do others and they
tried to make the rules of the game you
know match the things they wanted to do
and you know they ended up with this
language which is now used a lot in
um Quantum Computing because it's a very
sort of
like natural language for that problem
um
so
as to like how do you know what kinds of
things to draw well here like I was
trying to prove punctual reality which
is the sort of general property
and it says the thing you know says in
an abstract way the thing that I started
by saying which is like there I was I
wanted like h of GH to be the same as
eight yeah see here if you see this line
the update map the composite system you
see I've got
um HH after HG well I want that to be
the same as H just applied to H after G
and so that
that says okay well I want these two
things to be equal and so what I do is I
like draw the two diagrams for the two
parts
and they okay you draw them out and they
first of all they don't look equally
like oh that's annoying but then you
stare at it for a bit and you reflect on
the kind of moves that you're allowed to
make
you think well okay maybe I can
um
maybe I can apply this move and it makes
the diagrams look a bit more similar and
eventually you make the diagrams look
the same you've only used rules that
you're allowed to use
um okay I can see so skimming through to
see if it looks like that uh directly in
the thesis but like
effectively that's what's going on
um it's just the rules are a little bit
abstract though that being said
I know that um
sobocinski who's uh researcher in
category Theory at Tallinn he's got a
project
um with a colleague of his to build a a
mobile game
which is all about making string
diagrams equal in this way
um and so the idea is that in this game
you have like pictures like this and
you've got certain moves you can do to
manipulate the pictures
and that you know and the sort of aim of
the game is to like transform one the
sort of starting picture into like the
sort of gold picture just by applying
these moves and as you go through the
game the kind of moves you can do become
more complicated
um but it's I mean it's the same kind of
process I'm not sure the game is at the
stage now where you're allowed to like
do this like human creative thing and
think actually I want to like
make that be a new kind of move or
change the diagrams or like add in a
color here or something like that's a
really human thing and you know
designed to say you shouldn't do that
but I'm just trying to advocate for do
that in a way which is also rigorous
awesome awesome
yes
to speak fluently the syntax and the
grammar
whether we're talking about natural
human language or we're talking about
the active inference ontology
we want the syntax
to be unobtrusive if not compressient so
that we can actually convey the
semantics because that's the real
information flow
the syntax is within the Shannon signal
entropy space
and then in live stream 17 and 4D and
the physics as information processing
with Chris Fields where we've been
exploring these semantic Bayesian
information flows
that must out of necessity to be
enriched beyond the syntax have to
include an individual or shared context
that flow necessitates the proper syntax
and so
it's just um
part of the learning and so it's
exciting to see that there's games and
work like yours and others to help
because
um
if we could
play with those Legos
and get the instantaneous feedback just
like learning with a language tutor of
like no these two pieces they don't fit
together
and then it just it we kind of um would
actively infer
patterns make our own rules and
understandings
but there would be certain
compositionality of the system itself
and so it's interesting to think of like
you described it as a natural language
it is Technical and naturally arising
and our natural language without going
too much into the superior Wharf and
everything like that it reflects the
kind of subject object verb structure
that we often want to convey
this is a natural language for science
it conveys what we want to convey
and so being able to do that
in a way that is both disciplined and
rigorous
also enabling low cognitive overhead
fluency for some individuals today but
for more tomorrow that's just extremely
powerful and the fact that it has like
such a beautiful and intuitive way to
graphically represent it
is um very promising because that may
tap us into a more holistic
understanding and a visual field uh or a
felt sense understanding that just
looking at this and someone says wait
this is what we learn in active
inference it's like well no that's not
even the tip of the iceberg there's so
much more to it and it's not only this
and all of that but it's one of the
pieces that at this moment in time
in our sort of early calculator phase
or Abacus phase almost it's one of those
things that that we're tackling but it's
the wave that we're writing and I just
can't wait until there's more
accessibility and the learning Pathways
to to end up the playgrounds to use all
this yeah I mean I I totally agree with
with all of that and I I think um it was
it was nice to see the Jr in this
syllabus that included
um references to Eugenia Cheng's work
because she's done a lot of great work
to kind of make mathematics more
accessible in this way
um she had another article in the
guardian like in the last week or so
even talking about mathematics education
and how
um it's often
like it often like scares people because
they're
ought to like you just apply algorithms
in this kind of blind way to do like
multiplication or calculus or whatever
and and not really like play with the
concepts in the way that I assigned to
say okay well you know you're drawing
these diagrams and you know you want to
like play with them
and
it's
it would be nice to see mathematics
education take this kind of more playful
root to start with one of the things
that um Eugenia says in this article is
that unfortunately that would make
things kind of slower because like
you just want people to you know muck
around you don't want people just to you
know be able to churn out this kind of
computation but you know in this future
where our computational tools are so
powerful
maybe we don't all need to be perfect
integrators or like you know derivators
and be able to like multiply numbers
quickly and you know some people like
doing long division but I I don't even
remember how to see long division why
would I it's it's it's silly to kind of
drill that into children so they're
happy in projects
um
to teach like kindergarten children
um I like like a couple of projects not
many some of the kind of Rules of This
string diagrammatic stuff
um in in this Quantum
um information processing well this
um of book Bob Cooker and his colleagues
I think there was one
um I'll check by Dan geeker in
Birmingham and maybe one by Bob himself
or at least he was trying to get it off
the ground I don't remember
um but at least
where it has been tried I think they
found that children very easily learn to
use these
these these kinds of languages
um because it's just playing with
pictures they're kind of much more
approachable than this kind of scary
symbolic language
which is you know
I don't I mean it it's a kind of fine
language if you're used to like
piping on a typewriter or like writing
by hand where you're writing this linear
way
but you know if you go to like a
mathematics department and look at the
you know the whiteboards or the
chalkboards there you know most of the
time you see lots of pictures diagrams
and things and that's how people reason
typically
um and so a lot of what's been happening
with applied category theory is trying
to like
take using diagrams seriously as
mathematics
um and trying to like say okay well
here's what we can do if we do if we do
take it seriously we can sort of re-cap
we've sort of recapitulate
some of these things which people have
found like
abstract or abstruse or difficult
in mathematics before and like make them
seem a bit more
easy to reason with now and so I mean
that applies to like abstract things
like stuff I've mentioned already like a
Junctions like the laws of adjunctions
you can draw them with think string
diagrams I mean you know I haven't shown
it in my thesis but like you can
if you sort of Google around you can see
you know adjunctions in a two category
and they end up being some kind of
sneaky picture
and sort of you get a sense of like
what's going on there from these
pictures like the flow of information in
some sense
um and there's a similar thing with like
with limonas the the joke for like
functional programmers that they're
monads is like oh like you don't know
what a monad is well it's just a monoid
in the category of endo functors and I I
mean that's true it's not just a joke
it's true but the thing is if you draw
what a monoid is it's like a thing which
like like one of these like you see on
that picture you've got this Gauss thing
and it's got a black dot and you've got
you got one wire and then it has a black
dot and then two wires come out of it
and I said this is like copying
well like a monoid is like that in the
other direction like you've got two
things that go into a dots and that come
out with one thing so like when people
say monoi they mean something like they
often mean something like Edition you've
got two numbers that come together and
they produce one number or you've got
like multiplication you've got two
numbers again that come together and
produce one number
so like it's like the opposite of
copying in some abstract sense which
takes one thing and gives you two things
this is something that takes two things
and gives you one thing
and so you can just like draw the the
diagrams that Define a monoid and say
okay well what does this mean for like
Endo functions and you can sort of start
to reason about it a bit more
approachably I mean it's still quite
abstract because it is quite abstract
but it makes it kind of less scary to
use this kind of language I think
awesome
yeah
there's so much psychology
and sociology in mathematics and just
hearing about yeah on real chalkboards
people branch and they flow and they
Circle things and they put an X through
something it's like there's all these
operations that can't be copied
with a typewriter
and as are
uh cyber physical and social niches
develop
and we have different affordances
different metaphors different Quantum
reference frames for
working and being
it starts to make more sense
for uh having a natural language that
can express that
[Music]
um
yeah
then I go and I said laser stuff
it just makes me think of a touring tape
where even if there is a linear
representation it can still in some
other way characterize like a lisp
program with nesting or hierarchical
model even though yes there's like a
linearity but also there's a model so
it's not that we can't represent certain
things with the bit streams or anything
like that it's just that that may be
more like the Assembly Language and that
when we actually want to do certain
kinds of work we may want to just move
lightly and semantically with a high
level way to think about math
yeah totally it's kind of it's notable
to me that
um
like recently
I mean I've been giving you know talks
for a while you know using a computer
whether or not like over Zoom but like
it could be in person like you know have
my like PowerPoint slides or whatever
but these days if I give it a talk I
just use my like
top like digital tablet and I do
everything like all the slides by hand
and I draw pictures and it's nice now
that we've got like technology that's
starting to you know be a bit more human
in that sense and I think this is like a
kind of mathematical technology which is
like that although I think it's also
notable that
um it's still in some sense quite Niche
and I think I mean I don't I don't know
but the impression I've got from talking
to people is that it's still the case
that some mathematicians sort of think
of this kind of like mathematics of
diagrams that somehow like not quite
like real mathematics because it's like
it's too much like play in some sense
um but I think that I think that
perspective is changing and people are
taking it seriously I mean it is real
work and there's a lot of hard problems
um
and
you know stuff actually gets done but I
think it's
it doesn't to me it doesn't really
matter what like a handful of
mathematicians think it's just what's
useful to people that matters
um
and so I mean I I hope that you know
these tools continue to develop and like
you know we can use them in all sorts of
different domains
um
I don't know
you know I've never really
it's it's no it's like notable to me as
well that like human Vision it's kind of
like two and a bit dimensional really
it's not really like three-dimensional
but you've got a bit of
three-dimensionality and I've never
really played much with like
three-dimensional diagrams but maybe I
will one day have some tools with my
like you know Vision Pro or less not pro
thing or whatever it'll allow me to to
do things even more like naturally like
actually like plug together some stuff
in some abstract space
um who knows who knows
yeah
the diagram being two-dimensional or
planar
gives us this kind of classical screen
holographic screen that information can
be written on that then Quantum
cognitive agents can unfold into the
imaginary
plane with the wick rotation
but also the boundary just like you said
earlier can come in many shapes many
dimensionalities so we could have a four
dimensional boundary artifact
that still becomes rotated into a higher
dimension
and uh
that's not the framing or the
mathematics that most of us have learned
up to this point there's a really
crystallized would be a complementary
way to say it but um codified or
fossilized
sedimentary
understanding of math education its role
in broader thinking and what we learn
along the way
and the progressions get reified
with who makes it through the pipeline
so I think that's like
that's like the the unknown unknowns
here the known unknowns like we all know
that we struggle to understand this
but then what but but then that's the
real jumping off
when it when it's not just
us adapting into a new regime
of learning and doing but when there's
um
composition and construction within that
regime
in our last um sections here um Dean or
Ali another question or
um what what do you
looking to
Bridge or Gap into the dot too
Dean okay Elite please
uh well yeah I actually I've written
down a number of questions but uh they
maybe
um quite a specific and I think
um
they're perhaps best suited for the dot
two discussion but I wanted to thank
Toby for I mean I literally had
goosebumps the entire time
so uh it was really fascinating and uh
quite enjoyable and I uh learned a lot
and I hope to
I I also have some additional questions
in my mind I hope to uh get to get to
some of them in the second discussion uh
so yes thank you again it was really
really great
thanks
Dean with the penultimate thoughts what
do you um what do you see us heading
into
yeah well what
if it's if it's okay I'd like just to
read a really brief piece of the paper
because I don't want to watch on Toby in
the dot two without giving him a chance
to think about this a bit under 7-4
you've got fundamental Theory and you
say future work connected to this thesis
need not only be in applications a
number of purely theoretical questions
raise themselves too and I love 741 this
this one paragraph It's not
it's it's for me I call it a really have
to slow down and enjoy the moment you're
today Toby I don't know if you're a
distance Runner an endurance athlete of
some kind but your stamina has been
phenomenal but this one paragraph to me
would be like a refreshment station
where they offer you a milkshake and a
piece of battered fish like it's yummy
but you but you'd yeah you need to wait
you have to pause and go I don't know if
I want to do that but it really ties in
nicely with the syntax stuff that Danny
was talking about and I have a question
at the end of it so I just want to read
it though the mathematics of belief
so you basically said belief is
theoretical that's fantastic
is in large part about replacing defense
definite points with fuzzier
distributions over them independent type
Theory we've replaced points with terms
non-dependent terms are exactly points
so a type of theory with belief should
somehow Encompass fuzzy terms just as we
can replace points with distributions we
can replace dependent points with the
dependent distributions however the
standard replacement moving from a
category of functions to a category of
stochastic channels obscures some of the
universal categorical structure and
underpins the rules of type Theory this
standard replacement also misses
something else while it does allow for
fuzzy terms it omits a model of fuzzy
types
we might well want to express beliefs
about things whose identity we are not
quite sure and then you say in the next
sentence there seems to be a couple of
related resolutions to this puzzle my
question for you is this
and it's not for today it's maybe for
next time
um
it seems to me we have to Grapple with
this idea of making fuzzy clear and
making fuzzy precise and you started
speaking to that and my
my Wonder of coming now with a strong a
much stronger active inference set of
priors is there has to be something more
to this than just a gradient descent and
I think you started to
speak to that in this section and so
um
I'm kind of curious do you think that
this is a feature
the fact that we can do this we can do
fuzzy clear and fuzzy precise and not
necessarily see that as a contradiction
but actually the way category Theory
kind of gives us permission
to examine that so again it doesn't have
to be answered today
and maybe I'm maybe I'm misinterpreting
what you were trying to say there so I'm
I'm open to being redirected but I just
think that this opens up a world of
possibilities and when I first read it
um I I don't know like at least
Goosebumps looked like but I was just I
was just like oh man I really want to
ask you about this so yeah I mean yeah I
yeah so the thing about
fuzzy type yeah so I do I gotta start by
saying I agree the the kind of the what
some of this is seeking is something
like
thinking clearly about thinking fuzzly
in some ways kind of weird right
um it's like
having some certainty about uncertainty
um but it's definitely the case that
still now like I think
a notion of like fuzzy type theory is
not well developed though I am aware of
people
various people having thought about this
and people thinking about it at the
moment
um and of course I've got my own ideas
about it
um
but it seems natural right like we often
think we know what I think like we can
recognize a thing
but like
um
maybe you're not quite sure and so like
you know you're not sure if it's this or
that or you see somebody coming down the
street towards you and you can and
recognize them as somebody you know or
you used to know and then like as they
approach that their identity becomes a
bit clearer but you're not you know you
weren't sure for a while
um
and I think you know
there's nothing to say that
you know we shouldn't be able to you
know in some sense like types are a kind
of elements of some bigger space and so
we should be able to play all this math
to it and it's kind of really about
figuring out what the rules are that
makes the kind of language of type
Theory kind of align nicely with the
language of probability
um and it's a research effort but I'm
happy to talk about it like more next
time I'm also like happy to talk in any
detail about any of the actual like
specifics
of the stuff in the material in the
thesis or whatever else in category
Theory you might be interested in like
I'll probably be expert and everything
of course but I mean I'm happy to try my
best particularly if Ali it sounded like
your questions were maybe of like a more
technical nature maybe not if I I don't
know if I got the right sense of what
you were saying but if they are I'm
happy to like talk about the details of
that thank you sir I'd also like to like
review any of the stuff like to to try
to like say because I you're right that
there's a lot of like detail in the
thesis
um because you know you make a flame and
you're supposed to substantiate it and
that means you have to give a proof and
sometimes the proof is quite like
complicated
um
but like structurally I'm I'm I want
this to be simple or at least I have
like a simple like
framework and so I would like to be able
to like clarify some of that if that's
um if that's you know if there's time
for that or if it comes to it
yeah that sounds amazing in dot two we
will uh return perhaps any questions
that people submit as a comment on the
video or as a message in the category
Theory channel on our Discord we'll
curate those questions
wool re-watch and digest and then we can
begin with Ali asking some
um taking us on a little bit of a
technical journey and Toby thanks again
for the incredible work it's uh defined
our 2023 in many ways so it's been a joy
and we look forward to next week thanks
for plowing through
um I think yeah there's also the stuff I
I think we talked about before that that
we haven't really touched on this time
and obviously I didn't read much in the
pieces about like how do you actually
fit in like action into this framework
and like how do you like start to talk
about this like multi-agent stuff we can
you know your first time we can talk
about all of that
two of the pieces just to share that
that gave us some of the most laughs
were
um first
we didn't get action and and we're like
it's I mean just
the the the it wasn't an anti-climax it
was a climax of its own
and uh and then also we had had so many
discussions over the months of time and
the treatment of time backwards and
forwards ringing the bell unringing the
Bell
um all of these different concepts and
then in your limitations you said we we
really have to work on getting a
dynamical
treatment
oh yeah but I actually think that
depending on like what you care about it
may not be too hard so that's fine
but even that you would say it that way
just having dealt with time
oh yeah yeah and then to be like well I
mean it's like I thought that's what
dynamical modeling was involving time no
no so that that you're right you're
totally right there so all I meant at
that point was
the the the kind of like statistical
framework that I've been working with
until then it just seems you have like a
prior and like a way of make generating
predictions
but like the predict there's no like
nothing to say that the prior
has any like
data about how stuff actually evolves in
time or the predictions have any data
about how like the since data evolves in
time it's just like I believe that
there's this on the screen and that
makes there be this like stuff coming to
my eye and that's it this is like a
snapshot and so like when you want to
include time evolution in those beliefs
it Things become a bit more complicated
awesome well
thank you again Toby we'll see you
um in a week and a day
it's been a pleasure thank you for
having me
bye thank you so much
bye